Guide to the Lee Abbott Papers, circa 1965-2011 SPEC.RARE.CMS.0394
Ohio State University Libraries Special Collections
Lee Abbott Papers
circa 1965-2011
SPEC.RARE.CMS.0394
Ohio State University Libraries Special Collections
15.25 Cubic feet
As of 2018, Lee K. Abbott is professor emeritus of English at Ohio State University, and a writer of short stories, book reviews, and essays. He taught English at Case Western Reserve University from 1977 until 1989, and at Ohio State University from 1989 until his retirement in 2012. Abbott has published seven collections of his work. The Lee Abbott Papers contains drafts, proofs, and published copies of short stories, short story collections, book reviews, and essays written by Abbott. Also included are reviews of Abbott's work, and general articles and interviews about Abbott as a writer. Correspondence, materials related to his teaching activities, materials for speaking engagements in which he participated, and Abbott's typewriter and other personal materials are included as well. Materials are dated from circa 1965 to 2011.
(15) 5" legal document boxes; (12) 5" letter document boxes; (3) oversize document boxes; (1) artifact; (1) 2.5" legal document box
Abbott, Lee K.
Arrangement of Materials
Materials are arranged into 6 series:
Series 1: Fiction Series 2: Reviews and Essays Series 3: Correspondence Series 4: Teaching Series 5: Talks and Lectures Series 6: Personal
Acquisitions Information
Donated by: Lee K. Abbott, 2012 March
Access to Materials
Materials in box 31 have restricted access and may not be viewed without prior curatorial consent. The remainder of this collection is available for patron research, but may be used only in the Thompson Library Special Collections reading room.
Biographical Note
As of 2018, Lee K. Abbott (1947- ) is an American writer of short stories and professor emeritus of English at Ohio State University. He taught English at Case Western Reserve University from 1977 until 1989, when he began teaching at Ohio State University. Abbott was promoted to Humanities Distingushed Professor in 2007, and retired from Ohio State in 2012. Throughout his career he also taught as a writer in residence and a visiting faculty member at various academic institutions in the United States. Abbott's fiction has been published in literary journals and magazines, such as Harper's, The Atlantic Monthly, and The North American Review. He has published seven collections of his work, and his stories have been included in various other collections, including The Best American Short Stories. Abbott also reviewed books and works of other writers, and has written essays for newspaper and magazine columns. He has won fellowships from the National Endowment for the Arts and the Ohio Arts Council, was nominated twice for the Pulitzer Prize, has received numerous writing awards, and was awarded the Alumni Distinguished Teaching Award in 2004 from the Ohio State University.
Scope and Contents
The Lee Abbott Papers contains drafts and published copies of short stories in literary journals and magazines, in addition to drafts, proofs, galleys, contracts, book covers, and copyright agreements for his short story collections. Reviews of Abbott's work, publicity for his collections, and articles about awards he won for his work are also included. The collection also contains book reviews and essays written by Abbott, as well as copies of the newspapers and magazines they were published in. Also included are copies of interview questions and responses, and correspondence between Abbott and his colleagues, students, publishers, and academic institutions. The collection also consists of materials related to Abbott's teaching activities, including clippings, letters of recommendation for students, evaluations of student work and colleagues' performance, and fliers, programs and notes for his workshops and lectures. Clippings, drafts of speeches, fliers, and programs for Abbott's various speaking engagements are included as well. The collection also contains some of Abbott's personal materials, such as his typewriter, his Minister license, drafts of speeches for eulogies and a wedding, and various newspapers, magazines, and clippings. Materials are dated from circa 1965 to 2011.
Abbott, Lee K.; Authors, American--20th century; Authors, American--21st century; Books--Reviews--20th century; Books--Reviews--21st century; College teachers--Ohio--Cleveland--20th century; College teachers--Ohio--Columbus--20th century; College teachers--Ohio--Columbus--21st century; Critics in literature--20th century; Critics in literature--21st century; English teachers--Ohio--Cleveland--20th century; English teachers--Ohio--Columbus--20th century; English teachers--Ohio--Columbus--21st century; Galley proofs; Page proofs; Short stories, American--20th Century; Short stories, American--21st century; Short story--20th century; Short story--21st century; Tear sheets
- Fiction, 1979-2011; Series 1
  Access to Materials
  Materials in box 31 have restricted access and may not be viewed without prior curatorial consent.
  Scope and Contents
  Fiction contains manuscript drafts of short stories, copies of literary journals and magazines in which the stories were published, tearsheets, and reviews of Abbott's stories. Also included are drafts, proofs, galleys, publisher contracts, book covers, copyright agreements, reviews and publicity for Abbott's short story collections. Articles related to awards Abbott won for his writing, articles about Abbott as a fiction writer, and interviews with him are also included. Materials are arranged alphabetically by title of the story or collection, and chronologically within each title. Untitled manuscripts are listed at the end of the manuscripts, and articles and interviews related to Abbott's work as a fiction writer in general are listed chronologically at the end of the series. Materials date from 1979 to 2011.
  - "1913-1916" manuscript draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - "1963" manuscript drafts and published copy in the Tampa Review literary journal, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "All Things, All at Once" manuscript drafts, 1996 April-June (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - "All Things, All at Once" uncorrected author's proof and published copy in The Atlantic Monthly magazine, 1997 June, 1998 February (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - All Things, All at Once collection manuscript draft, circa 2005 (Box 14, Folder 7, Box 15, Folder 1-6)
  - All Things, All at Once collection master set proof, first pass, 2005 September 12 (Box 14, Folder 1, Box 13, Folder 8)
  - All Things, All at Once collection master set proof, second pass, 2005 November 13 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - All Things, All at Once collection master set proof, third pass, 2005 December 7 (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in Another Chicago Magazine photocopy, circa 2006 (Box 23, Folder 58)
  - All Things, All at Once collection unbound pages, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - All Things, All at Once collection advanced reading copy, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - All Things, All at Once collection partial proof with editor notes, 2006 January 9 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - All Things, All at Once collection digital proofs copy, 2006 February 1 (Box 13, Folder 6-7)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in Library Journal tearsheets, 2006 April 17 (Box 23, Folder 22)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in Library Journal tearsheet, 2006 May 1 (Box 23, Folder 63)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in Booklist tearsheet, 2006 June (Box 23, Folder 60)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in Milwaukee Journal Sentinel printout and tearsheet, 2006 June 9-11 (Box 23, Folder 64)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review and comments on the Emerging Writers Network website printout, 2006 June 16 (Box 23, Folder 18)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in The San Diego Union-Tribune tearsheet, 2006 June 18 (Box 23, Folder 70)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in Florida Newspaper tearsheet, 2006 July 5 (Box 23, Folder 62)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in Dallas Morning News tearsheet and published copy, 2006 July 9 (Box 23, Folder 61)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review from the Baltimore Sun, 2006 July 16 (Box 23, Folder 59)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in Montecito Journal clipping, 2006 July 20-August 2 (Box 23, Folder 65)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in The News & Observer clipping and tearsheets, 2006 July 23 (Box 23, Folder 68)
  - All Things, All at Once collection Barnes & Noble book search printout, 2006 July 29 (Box 23, Folder 19)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in The New York Times Book Review clipping and copies, 2006 August 6 (Box 23, Folder 66)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in The New York Times Book Review and bestseller list copies, 2006 August 13 (Box 23, Folder 67)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in The Plain Dealer tearsheet, 2006 August 13 (Box 23, Folder 69)
  - All Things, All at Once collection review in Sunday Denver Post and Rocky Mountain News tearsheets, 2006 August 27 (Box 23, Folder 71)
  - "As Fate Would Have It" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Be Free, Die Young" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "The Beauty of Drink: An Essay" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Billy Jack Eddy's Stories Behind the Hits" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Category Z" manuscript draft, marked set uncorrected proof and published copy in The Atlantic, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Chapter Four: The Moment of Inertia" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Collected Stories contract with W.W. Norton & Company, Inc., 2004 November 10 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - A Collection of Classic Southern Humor contract and clipping, 1984 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - "The Cowboys of New Mexico Explain Where All Stories Come From" and "The Drinking Habits of Cowboys" poem manuscripts, undated (Box 17, Folder 24)
  - "The Cowboys of New Mexico Respond to a Question of Usage" poem, published copy in Poetry Now journal, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - "A Creature Out of Palestine" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "Demons" manuscript draft and photocopy of "Redemption" by John Gardner, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - "Dreams of Distant Lives" manuscript drafts, proof and published copy in Harper's Magazine, correspondence with Harper's editor, and review clipping, 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection unedited manuscript, circa 1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection manuscript with front matter, circa 1988 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection edited manuscript with front matter, circa 1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection galley, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection galley, duplicate pages, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection master galley, first pass, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection author's galley, 1988 October (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection master galley, 1988 December (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection master galley, second pass, 1988 December (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection book covers for White Pine Press and Putnam Publishing editions, 1989, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection selected galley pages with editor notes, 1989 January-February (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection blueline proof, 1989 February 7 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection reviews, 1989 February-September (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection reviews, 1989 April, December (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection, Northern Ohio LIVE's Award of Achievement magazine, 1989 September 22 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection contract between White Pine Press and G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1990 May 1 (Box 17, Folder 28)
  - Dreams of Distant Lives collection Ohioana Book Award for Fiction newspaper clipping, 1990 October 15 (Box 17, Folder 27)
  - "Driving His Buick Home" manuscript drafts and published copy in The North American Review, 1988 March (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "The Eldest of Things" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The End of Grief" manuscript drafts and published copy in The Atlantic, 1985 August (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "The Era of Great Numbers" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "The Final Proof of Fate and Circumstance" manuscript draft and literary analysis photocopied from Masterplots II, circa 1983, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "The Final Proof of Fate and Circumstance" clipping, 1984 October 7 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - "Freedom, a Theory Of" manuscript drafts and notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "Getting Even" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "Gravity" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - "A Great Piece of Elephant" manuscript drafts and correspondence with Stephen Corey, 2007 January (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - "The Hands That Feed You" manuscript draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - "The Happy Parts" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Having the Human Thing of Joy" manuscript drafts, 1984 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Heart Never Fits Its Wanting collection awards correspondence, program, and certificate, 1980, 1982 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - "The Heart Never Fits Its Wanting" reviews, 1980 December-1981 April (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - "The Heart Never Fits Its Wanting" reviews and clippings, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Heart Never Fits Its Wanting" manuscript draft and photocopy of published copy in The Ohio Review, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Here in Time and Not" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "How Love is Lived in Paradise" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "How One Becomes Another" clipping, 1996 December 22 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - "How One Becomes the Other" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "The Human Use of Inhuman Beings" manuscript drafts and research, 1988-1993 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - "I'm Glad You Asked" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "In the Yonder World" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Living After Midnight collection bound uncorrected proofs, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Living After Midnight collection books covers and negative for Putnam Publishing and Ohio State University Press editions, 1991, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Living After Midnight collection copyright registration, award announcement, 1991 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    Restricted; contains financial information
  - Living After Midnight collection reviews, 1991-1992 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Living After Midnight collection reviews, 1991-1993 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Living After Midnight collection copy editor's master manuscript, 1992 September 2 (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
  - Living After Midnight novella manuscript draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Living After Midnight novella manuscript draft and notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - "Living Alone in Iota" in O. Henry Awards clipping, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - "Living Alone in Iota" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Looking for Love in New Mexico" manuscript draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Louder Than Words collection clippings, 1990 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - "Love and the Hurt of It" manuscript drafts and notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Love Is the Crooked Thing" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Love Is the Crooked Thing collection manuscript, circa 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Love Is the Crooked Thing collection awards announcements, 1986 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Love Is the Crooked Thing collection book covers for Ohio State University Press and Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill editions, 1986, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Love Is the Crooked Thing collection reviews, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Makin' Whoopee" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - "A Man Bearing Snow" manuscript drafts and notes, 1991-1992 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "A Man Bearing Snow" manuscript drafts and notes, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Martians contract with G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1988 July 6 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    Restricted, contains personally identifiable information
  - "The Meaning of Life" manuscript draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - "Men of Rough Persuasion" manuscript drafts and correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - "A Modern Story of Woe and Lovecraft" manuscript drafts and notes, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Near the Heart-Place of Grue" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Never Up, Never In" story included in The Putt at the End of the World collection, author's proof and review in People magazine, 1999 December, 2000 July 3 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - "Notes I Made on the Man I Was" manuscript drafts, 1984 August 8 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "On Tuesday Nothing, on Wednesday Walls" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - "On Sunday" manuscript draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - "One More Thing About Then" manuscript drafts and published copy in The North American Review, 1992 November-December (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - "One of Star Wars, One of Doom" manuscript drafts, notes, correspondence, and research, 1999-2001 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "Once Upon a Time" story included in Fault Lines collection, book jacket, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - "Once Upon a Time" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "The Other Story of Love and Forgiveness" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - "The Other World I See" manuscript drafts and published copy in The North American Review, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Pink" manuscript draft, publisher agreement and correspondence with Tin House Magazine, 2011 May-August (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - "Precious but Gone Are the Hours We Touched, Etc." manuscript drafts, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Purpose of This Creature Man" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Revolutionaries" manuscript drafts, proof and published copy in The Atlantic, 1987 February (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "Rolling Thunder" manuscript drafts and published copy in the Memphis State Review, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "The Second Meaning of It All" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - "Stand in a Row and Learn" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "The Story As I Know It" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection manuscript, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 1-5, Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection proof, copy 1, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection contract with G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1985 December 16 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    Restricted, contains financial information
  - Strangers in Paradise collection proof, copy 2, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection book covers for Ohio State University Press and G.P. Putnam's Sons editions, 1986, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection galley, 1986 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection galley, 1986 April 29 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection reviews, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection uncorrected proofs for G.P. Putnam's Sons edition, 1987 January (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection reviews, 1987 January-February (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Strangers in Paradise collection copyright registration form, 1987 February 25 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    Restricted; contains financial information.
  - Strangers in Paradise collection reviews and book jacket summary, 1987-1988, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - "Sweet Cheeks" manuscript drafts, proof and published copy in Harper's Magazine, 1990 March-October (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "The Talk Talked Between Worms" manuscript drafts, 1995 March-April (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Time and Fear and Somehow Love" award announcement, 1986 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - "Time and Fear and Somehow Love" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "The Unfinished Business of Childhood" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "The Valley of Sin" manuscript draft and literary analysis photocopied from Masterplots II, circa 1985, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "The Viet Cong Love of Sgt. Donnie T. Bobo" manuscript draft and published copy in The North American Review magazine, 1979 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The View of Me from Mars" manuscript drafts, proofs and published copy in Harper's Magazine, 1988 March, June (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "The Way Sin is Said in Wonderland" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - "We Get Smashed and Our Endings Are Swift" manuscript drafts and notes, circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Wet Places at Noon collection manuscript draft, circa 1997 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Wet Places at Noon collection manuscript with publisher's notes, 1997 May (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - Wet Places at Noon collection uncorrected page proofs, 1997 June (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Wet Places at Noon collection proof, 1997 June (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
  - Wet Places at Noon collection reviews, 1997 September-1998 January (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Wet Places at Noon collection book cover for University of Iowa Press edition, circa 2009 (Box 23, Folder 21)
  - Wet Places at Noon collection review printout from The University of Iowa News Services, 2009 August 31 (Box 23, Folder 20)
  - Wet Places at Noon collection manuscript draft with early title ( The Human Use of Inhuman Beings), undated (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - "What Jesus Says" manuscript drafts and published copy in The North American Review, 1980 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "What She's Saying Now" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - "When Our Dream World Finds Us, and These Hard Times Are Gone" published copy in Loyola University's New Orleans Review, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "When Our Dream World Finds Us, and These Hard Times are Gone" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - "Where Is Garland Steeples Now?" manuscript drafts and illustrated excerpt, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "The Who, the What and the Why" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Why I Live in Hanoi" manuscript drafts and research articles, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "The World Is Almost Rotten" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "The World of Apples" manuscript drafts and published copy in Nit & Wit magazine, 1986 December (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "X" manuscript drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Youth on Mars" manuscript drafts, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Untitled manuscripts, undated (Box 18, Folder 1-10, Box 19, Folder 33, Box 23, Folder 29)
  - Articles about Abbott as a fiction writer, 1984-1989 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Articles and clippings about Abbott as a fiction writer, 1987-1992 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - Articles about Abbott as a fiction writer, 1991-2009 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Interview by Andrew Scott, questions and responses draft, circa 2006 (Box 23, Folder 34)
  - Interview question responses, undated (Box 24, Folder 12)
- Reviews and Essays, 1978-2009; Series 2
  Reviews and Essays contains manuscript drafts of book reviews, essays, and literary journal reviews written by Abbott. Also included are copies of the newspapers and magazines in which his reviews and essays were published. Materials date from 1978 to 2009, and are arranged alphabetically by title of the review or essay, or title of the work being reviewed, with untitled and unidentified manuscripts listed at the end of the series.